A Finding Aid to the Humberto Dionisio Papers, 1919-1990, in the Archives of American Art AAA.dionhumb
Archives of American Art
Humberto Dionisio papers
1919-1990
AAA.dionhumb
Archives of American Art
2.6 Linear feet
The papers of painter Humberto Dionisio measure 2.6 linear feet and date from 1919 to 1990. The collection primarily documents Dionisio's relationships with his family, particularly his mother, through letters, photographs, financial records, printed material, and family memorabilia collected by Dionisio himself and by his mother, Zaida Ortega Dominguez.
Humberto Dionisio
Biographical Note
Humberto Dionisio was born in Cuba in 1950. During the 1970s he became a noted poster artist and completed his studies in Graphic Design at the Consejo Nacional de Cultura in Cuba in 1975. He arrived in Miami, Florida, via the Mariel boat lift in 1980, and achieved success in Miami as a painter from the mid to late 1980s. He died in March 1987 at the age of thirty-six.
Scope and Content Note
The collection measures 2.6 linear feet, dates from 1919 to 1990, and includes letters, photographs, financial records, printed material, and family memorabilia. The papers of Dionisio primarily document his relationships with other family members and friends through photographs and letters received from his mother, Zaida Ortega Dominguez, and others. The collection also contains papers, photographs and original sketches (by Dominguez) collected by Dominguez herself which were in Dionisio's care. Papers relating specifically to Dionisio's work as an artist are represented to a lesser degree in this collection and consist primarily of printed material and photographs of Dionisio at work and at an exhibition of his work. There is also one original watercolor by Dionisio from 1985.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series. Each series is arranged into subseries according to record type.
Series 1: Humberto Dionisio Papers, 1926-1990, undated (Boxes 1-3; 1.7 linear feet)
Series 2: Zaida Ortega Dominguez Papers, 1919-circa 1980s, undated (Boxes 4-6; 0.9 linear feet)
Provenance
The Humberto Dionisio papers were donated by Jim Kitchens, a friend of Dionisio, in 1996.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington, D.C. research facility.
Dominquez, Zaida Ortega; Rodriguez, Zoraida; Saavedra, Nelia Dominguez; Artists--Cuba; Cuba--Social life and customs; Cuban American art; Cuban American artists; Cuban Americans--Florida--Miami; Expatriate artists--Florida--Miami; Hispanic American artists; Photographs
- Humberto Dionisio Papers, 1926-1990, undated; Series 1; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Scope and Contents note
  The bulk of this series consists of letters and photographs. Letters are primarily from Dionisio's mother, Zaida Ortega Dominguez, and are generally in Spanish.
  Arrangement note
  The series is arranged into eight subseries.
  1.1: Biographical Material, 1974-1987, undated
  1.2: Letters, 1980-1987, undated
  1.3: Business Papers, 1980-1986
  1.4: Notes, undated
  1.5: Writings, 1978-1980, undated
  1.6: Clippings, 1975-1990, undated
  1.7: Photographs, 1950-1984, undated
  1.8: Michael Ford File, 1926, 1951, 1987-1990, undated
  - Biographical Material, 1974-1987, undated; 1.1
    The biographical material found in this subseries consists primarily of the contents of two wallets, including photographs of Dionisio and family members and identification cards. The subseries also contains diplomas and awards, a resumé, and financial and medical records.
    - Brown Wallet, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Contents of Brown Wallet, 1983-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Contents of Red Wallet, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Diplomas and Awards, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      See also OV 7.
    - Resumé, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Birth Certificate, Exit Papers, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - St. Kevins Catholic School, Dade County Public School, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Health Benefits Information, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Income Tax Papers, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Invoice from Bloomingdale's, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Unemployment Benefits, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Miscellany, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters, 1980-1987, undated; 1.2
    In addition to letters from Dionisio's mother, this subseries also contains letters from his grandmother, Nelia Dominguez Saavedra, and his cousin, dancer Zoraida Rodriguez, which were written between Dionisio's departure from Cuba in 1980 and his death in 1987. The letters frequently mention social and political events in Cuba and the envelopes are often decorated with colorful pictures of Cuban writers and political heroes, as well as fauna and flora of the island. Several letters include clippings from Cuban newspapers regarding art exhibitions and films. Letters from Zoraida Rodriguez include clippings and programs of the "Ballet de Camaguey" in which she was one of the principal dancers. Also found here are letters from Zaida Ortega Dominguez addressed to other family members living in Miami. Three letters from Dominguez to Dionisio, dated 1987, were received unopened.
    - Letters, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 13-27)
    - Letters from Lovers, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Letters from Friends and Other Family, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Letters from Dionisio to Grandmother, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Greeting Cards to Dionisio, 1981-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Business Papers, 1980-1986; 1.3
    This subseries contains routine business and legal records.
    - Gene Barry Volkswagen, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Crawford and Company (Attorneys), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Car Accident Papers, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - State of Florida Department of Highway Safety and Motor Vehicles, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Utah Home Fire Insurance Company, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Miscellany, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Notes, circa 1990, undated; 1.4
    This subseries contains guest and price lists for several exhibitions of Dionisio's work, including a 1990 retrospective exhibition at the InterAmerican Art Gallery. Handwritten notes, and lists of names and addresses can also be found here.
    - Guest Lists for Axes and Retrospective, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Handwritten Notes, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - List of Names and Addresses, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Price Lists and Lists of Works in Humberto Dionisio Retrospective, circa 1990 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Writings, 1978-1980, undated; 1.5
    This series contains several poems in addition to an essay by Giulio V. Blanc about Dionisio.
    - Writings by Giulio V. Blanc About Humberto Dionisio and the Expresiónes Hispanas Exhibition, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Poems by Dionisio, for Dioniso, and for Damian by Carlos Manuel Ortego, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Printed Material, 1975-1990, undated; 1.6
    Found here are clippings about Dionisio and other artists, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and handwritten and printed versions of a eulogy written for Dionisio by Carlos Alfonzo.
    - Clippings, 1976, 1982, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Clippings About Other Artists, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Invitations, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Exhibition Announcements for Dionisio Exhibitions, 1987, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Exhibition Catalog, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Exhibition Announcements for Group Shows with Dionisio, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Carlos Alfonzo's Eulogy for Dionisio, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Periodical El Mariel, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Material, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Photographs, 1950-1984, undated; 1.7
    In addition to loose photographs of Dionisio with family and friends, this subseries contains two photograph albums of snapshots of Dionisio with family and friends, in addition to photographs of Dionisio at work, and at an exhibition of his work.
    - Loose Pages from Albums, 1980-1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Two Photograph Albums, 1980-1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
    - Photographs of Dionisio and Friends, 1981, 1984, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Photographs of Dionisio's Work, 1977, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Photographs of Dionisio's Calle Ocho, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Photographs of Dionisio and Immediate Family, circa 1950-1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Photographs of Dionisio Alone and with Friends and Family, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Photographs of Dionisio, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Photographs of Dionisio as a Child, circa 1950-1954 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Michael Ford File, 1926, 1951, 1985-1990, undated; 1.8
    This subseries consists of a small amount of material kept by Michael Ford, a friend of Dionisio, including correspondence, photocopies of artwork, an original watercolor by Dioniso, and printed material.
    - Correspondence, 1987, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Color Photocopies of Artwork, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Printed Material, 1926, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 11-13)
    - Original Print by Unknown Artist, undated (Box OV 7)
    - Original Watercolor by Dionisio, 1985 (Box OV 7)
- Zaida Ortega Dominguez Papers, 1919-circa 1980s, undated; Series 2; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 4-6
  Papers of Dioniso's mother primarily consist of photographs of family and friends in addition to family memorabilia, artwork by Dominguez, letters, and printed material. Certain items relate to Dionisio's brother, Ricardo Padron Ortega, and his father, Humberto Ysidro Padron Fernández.
  2.1: Biographical Material, 1919-1980, undated
  2.2: Letters and Printed Material, 1979-circa 1981, undated
  2.3: Photographs, circa 1920-1980s, undated
  2.4: Artwork, circa 1930s, 1972, undated
  - Biographical Material, 1919-1980, undated; 2.1
    Found here are family records such as birth and marriage certificates and baby memorabilia.
    - Ricardo Padron Ortega Funeral Document and Doctor's Certificate, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - First Communion Certificate of Ricardo Padron Ortega, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Ricardo Padron Ortega's Baby Book, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Lock of Hair with Handwritten Note, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Zaida Ortega Dominguez Birth Certificate, 1919 (stamped 1980) (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Zaida Ortega Dominguez Marriage Certificate, 1949 (stamped 1979) (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Humberto Ysidro Padron Fernández Birth Certificate, 1922 (signed 1968) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Letters and Printed Material, 1979-circa 1981, undated; 2.2
    Found here are poems, greeting and sympathy cards, notes, and a clipping.
    - Poem from Ricardo Padron Ortega to Dominguez, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Sympathy Card from Friends to Dominguez upon the Death of Ricardo Padron Ortega, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Greeting Cards to Dominguez, circa 1981 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Handwritten Notes from Ricardo Padron Ortega to Dominguez, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Clipping Concerning Bridal Shower of Friend, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, circa 1920-1980s, undated; 2.3
    This subseries forms the bulk of the series and contains photographs of family and friends including Dionisio as an infant and throughout his life.
    - Portraits of Family and Friends, circa 1930s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Photographs of Family and Friends, Group Shots, circa 1930-1980s (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
    - Photographs of Family and Friends, circa 1930s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Photographs of Children, Family and Friends, circa 1930-1980s (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Dominguez's Grade School Graduation Photographs, circa 1926-1936 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Photographs of Dominguez, circa 1920-1980s (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Polaroids of Family and Friends, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Photographs of Dominguez and Humberto Ysidro Padron Fernández (Husband), circa 1940-1950s (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Photographs of Dionisio's Brothers as Children, circa 1952-1955 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Photographs of Dominguez with Second Husband, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Framed Photograph of Unidentified Man, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Photographs of Baptism, Wedding, Bridal Shower and Dinner Banquet, 1945, 1953, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Photographs of Dominguez and Unidentified Woman, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Artwork, circa 1930s, 1972, undated; 2.4
    This subseries consists of a group of original sketches and drawings by Dominguez, primarily of Hollywood personalities.
    - Original Drawings, circa 1930s, 1972, undated (Box 6, Folder 4-5)